Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and today we're talking about someone who's very, very dirty.
我是Catherine，今天我们聊一个非常非常脏的人。
That's right and actually not only are we talking about something being dirty but also
没错，而且我们不仅聊脏东西，还聊到
that we want to clean everything.
我们想把一切都弄干净。
Okay, so you'll learn how to call someone who likes clean things in English today.
好的，所以今天你会学到如何用英语称呼喜欢干净的人。
Let's take a listen to our dialogue.
我们来听听对话。
This bathroom is a pig's die.
这浴室简直是个猪圈。
Helen, why do you keep flushing the toilet?
海伦，你为什么一直冲马桶？
What's wrong?
怎么了？
I just can't stand it.
我就是受不了。
It's really gross in here.
这里太恶心了。
There's a stain on the toilet seat and the floor was wet and slippery so I cleaned it.
马桶座上有污渍，地板又湿又滑，所以我清理了。
You did what?
你做了什么？
Helen, I know it's gross but I've seen many public washrooms that are much worse.
海伦，我知道很恶心，但我见过更糟的公共厕所。
Why are you cleaning the countertop?
你为什么在擦台面？
Are you out of your mind?
你疯了吗？
I can't help myself.
我控制不住自己。
It's just so disgusting in here.
这里实在太恶心了。
Helen, this is not like your own bathroom.
海伦，这不是你自己的浴室。
Just leave it to the cleaners, okay?
留给清洁工处理，好吗？
Hang on, I'm just going to quickly wipe the sink and sweep the floor.
等等，我很快擦一下水槽，再扫个地。
You're such a neat freak.
你真是个洁癖狂。
I'm out of here.
我走了。
Alright we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So this girl was very much of a neat freak and we're going to take a look at that word
所以这个女孩是个十足的洁癖狂，我们稍后会仔细看看这个词。
a little bit later on.
稍后再说。
Why don't we go back to the very beginning and take a look at some vocab on Language
我们不如回到开头，看看“语言要点”里的词汇。
Takeaway.
语言要点。
Language Takeaway
The first word we have here on Language Takeaway today is pigsty.
今天“语言要点”的第一个词是“pigsty”。
This bathroom is a pigsty.
这浴室是个猪圈。
Okay, so pigsty is a place where pigs live.
好的，“pigsty”是猪住的地方。
Now this obviously, the bathroom is not really a place where pigs live so if you call something
显然，浴室不是猪住的地方，所以如果你说某处是“pigsty”，
a pigsty, you're saying that it's very dirty.
就是说它很脏。
You're saying it's disgusting.
就是说它很恶心。
It's very, very dirty like a pigsty.
非常非常脏，像猪圈一样。
So actually if you go to a farm and you see where all the pigs are, that is actually called
实际上，如果你去农场，看到猪待的地方，
a pigsty.
那才叫“pigsty”。
Right, there's mud and dirt and yeah, that's a pigsty.
对，有泥巴和脏东西，那就是猪圈。
So someone who is very, very dirty, you can also call a pig.
所以一个非常非常脏的人，你也可以叫他“pig”。
Okay, now she was saying that the bathroom is so dirty and it's really gross in here.
好的，她说浴室很脏，而且这里真的很恶心。
Okay, so gross means something is, she doesn't like it.
好的，“gross”意思是她不喜欢的东西。
It's really dirty and you know, makes her uncomfortable.
真的很脏，让她不舒服。
So something that doesn't taste good, you can say it's gross.
所以不好吃的东西，你可以说它“gross”。
That's right.
没错。
So I don't like to eat snake.
所以我不喜欢吃蛇肉。
I think eating snake is gross.
我觉得吃蛇肉很恶心。
Okay, very good.
好的，很好。
So something that is gross is something that's not really nice, maybe it tastes bad or it
所以“gross”的东西是不太好的，可能味道差，
smells bad, something that is bad in general.
或者气味难闻，总之是不好的东西。
That's right.
没错。
Okay, so she went on to talk about the toilet seat and that there was a stain on the toilet
好的，然后她继续聊到马桶座，说马桶座上有污渍。
seat.
马桶座上有污渍。
Okay, a stain is usually a bad thing.
好的，“stain”通常是个坏东西。
It means that there's a color or a mark that's permanent or maybe can be washed away on something.
意思是某物上有一个颜色或痕迹，可能是永久的，或者可以洗掉。
So in this case, the toilet seat has a mark on it.
所以这里，马桶座上有个印记。
Maybe it's brown or yellow, but I can also say, I was drinking wine and I spilled the
可能是棕色或黄色，但我也可以说，我喝红酒时，
wine on my shirt and it left a stain.
洒在衬衫上，留下了污渍。
So now there's always this red part on my shirt.
所以现在衬衫上总有这块红色。
It won't go away.
去不掉。
Okay, so a stain is a mark that usually won't go away.
好的，所以“stain”是通常去不掉的印记。
So then she went on to describe the bathroom as being disgusting.
然后她继续描述浴室很恶心。
So I guess this is very similar to gross.
所以我想这和“gross”很相似。
That's right.
没错。
Something that is gross is usually also disgusting.
“gross”的东西通常也“disgusting”。
I can say, oh, this food is awful.
我可以说，哦，这食物糟透了。
It's just disgusting.
真恶心。
But I can also say in this case, oh, your room is disgusting.
但这里我也可以说，哦，你的房间真恶心。
You need to clean it.
你得打扫一下。
It's so dirty or bad or unappealing.
太脏、太差或太不吸引人。
So something that is gross, something that is disgusting is something negative.
所以“gross”和“disgusting”的东西都是负面的。
And then we have our keyword and the title of this lesson for today, a neat freak.
然后我们有今天的关键词和课程标题，“neat freak”。
Her friend says, you're such a neat freak.
她朋友说，你真是个洁癖狂。
That's right.
没错。
So a neat freak is someone who likes things to be very clean.
所以“neat freak”是喜欢东西非常干净的人。
And so a neat freak does not live in a pigsty.
所以洁癖狂不住在猪圈里。
A neat freak does not like to be in pigsties.
洁癖狂不喜欢待在猪圈里。
A neat freak likes things to be in order and organized and clean.
洁癖狂喜欢东西井井有条、整洁干净。
So maybe somebody that's cleaning all the time or that's very, very organized, you can
所以可能有人一直在打扫，或者非常有条理，你可以
say that that person is a neat freak.
说那个人是个洁癖狂。
He is a neat freak or she is a neat freak.
他是个洁癖狂，或者她是个洁癖狂。
Now it's not necessarily a good thing to be a neat freak, but it's not terrible either
当个洁癖狂不一定是好事，但也不是坏事。
to call somebody a neat freak.
叫某人洁癖狂。
You can say, hey, are you a neat freak?
你可以说，嘿，你是个洁癖狂吗？
Right.
对。
That means, are you really concerned about cleanliness?
意思是，你非常在意清洁吗？
Uh-huh.
嗯哼。
OK.
好的。
Very good.
很好。
So a lot of great vocab.
所以有很多很棒的词汇。
Take a look again at our dialogue and we'll be back in a bit.
再看一遍我们的对话，我们一会儿回来。
This bathroom is a pigsty.
这浴室简直是个猪圈。
Helen, why do you keep flushing the toilet?
海伦，你为什么老冲马桶？
What's wrong?
怎么了？
I just can't stand it.
我就是受不了。
It's really gross in here.
这里太恶心了。
There's a stain on the toilet seat and the floor was wet and slippery, so I cleaned it.
马桶座上有污渍，地板又湿又滑，所以我清理了。
You did what?
你做了什么？
Helen, I know it's gross, but I've seen many public washrooms that are much worse.
海伦，我知道很恶心，但我见过更糟的公共厕所。
Why are you cleaning the countertop?
你为什么在擦台面？
Are you out of your mind?
你疯了吗？
I can't help myself.
我控制不住自己。
It's just so disgusting in here.
这里实在太恶心了。
Helen, this is not like your own bathroom.
海伦，这不是你自己的浴室。
Just leave it to the cleaners, OK?
留给清洁工处理，好吗？
Hang on.
等等。
I'm just going to quickly wipe the sink and sweep the floor.
我只要快速擦一下水槽，扫一下地。
You're such a neat freak.
你真是个洁癖狂。
I'm out of here.
我走了。
All right.
好吧。
We're back.
我们回来了。
So now let's take a look at Fluency Builder.
现在来看看流利度提升部分。
Fluency Builder.
流利度提升。
So the first thing we want to talk about today is this phrase, I can't stand it.
所以今天要讲的第一个短语是“我受不了了”。
So this is our neat freak talking.
这是我们的洁癖狂在说话。
She says, I just can't stand it.
她说，我就是受不了。
I just can't stand it.
我就是受不了。
So if you can't stand something, that means that you can't tolerate it.
所以如果你受不了某事，意思是你无法容忍它。
That's right.
没错。
It means I don't like it.
意思就是我不喜欢它。
I don't want it anymore.
我不想再要它了。
I need to change it.
我需要改变它。
OK.
好的。
So for example, if a bar is too loud, you say, I have to leave.
比如，如果酒吧太吵，你会说，我得走了。
I can't stand it.
我受不了了。
It's too loud in there.
里面太吵了。
That's right.
没错。
Or if you are next to me all day and you do tap, tap, tap, tap, tap with your pen, I say,
或者如果你整天在我旁边用笔敲啊敲，我会说，
Marco, stop it.
马可，停下。
I can't stand it anymore.
我再也受不了了。
OK, very good.
好的，很好。
And then she went on to explain or to justify why she was cleaning the public restroom.
然后她继续解释或辩解为什么在打扫公共厕所。
And she said, I can't help myself.
她说，我控制不住自己。
It's just too disgusting in here.
这里实在太恶心了。
I can't help myself.
我控制不住自己。
So this means that I cannot control my actions.
所以这意思是我无法控制自己的行为。
OK, I cannot control what I do.
好的，我无法控制自己做的事。
And so in some cases, like with a neat freak, the person really needs everything to be clean.
所以在某些情况下，比如洁癖狂，这个人真的需要一切都干净。
And so she says, I can't help myself.
所以她说，我控制不住自己。
I have to clean.
我必须打扫。
OK, so it's a phrase like this.
好的，就是这样的短语。
Don't try to separate it and try to define what help and help yourself.
不要试图拆开它，去定义“help”和“help yourself”。
It's more of a phrase saying, I can't control myself.
它更像一个短语，意思是“我控制不住自己”。
I can't control my actions.
我无法控制自己的行为。
I can't help myself.
我控制不住自己。
Or in the case of another person, you say, she can't help herself.
或者对另一个人，你说，她控制不住自己。
She can't help himself.
他控制不住自己。
Right, so maybe you'd like to smoke.
对，比如你可能喜欢抽烟。
And you're smoking all the time.
你一直在抽烟。
And you say, stop smoking.
你说，别抽了。
You say, I can't help myself.
你说，我控制不住自己。
I have to smoke.
我必须抽。
Yeah, I have to smoke.
是的，我必须抽。
OK, and for our last phrase, she said, hang on.
好的，最后一个短语，她说，等等。
I'm just going to quickly wipe the sink and sweep the floor.
我只要快速擦一下水槽，扫一下地。
Hang on.
等等。
This means wait.
这意思是等一下。
Wait a moment.
等一会儿。
Yeah.
是的。
Yeah, so this is a really common phrase we hear in English.
是的，这是我们在英语中经常听到的一个短语。
It's something that you'll hear all the time in a pretty relaxed environment, not maybe
你会在非常轻松的环境里经常听到它，可能不会
in school.
在学校里。
But if someone says, OK, I'm going to go.
但如果有人说，好了，我要走了。
See you later.
回头见。
And the other person wants to say something to you, say, hang on.
而另一个人想对你说点什么，就说，等一下。
Hang on.
等一下。
Wait a moment.
等一会儿。
I have to tell you this thing.
我得告诉你这件事。
So you wouldn't really use it with your boss or a customer.
所以你通常不会对老板或客户用这个。
You wouldn't say, hang on a second.
你不会说，等一下。
No, you would say that with a friend or family member, things like that.
不，你会对朋友或家人说这类话。
OK, so it's a very informal way of saying, wait a moment.
好的，所以这是一种非常非正式的说法，意思是“等一会儿”。
Wait a minute.
等一分钟。
That's right.
没错。
So the formal way is, please wait.
所以正式的说法是，请稍等。
Please wait.
请稍等。
And the informal way is, hang on.
而非正式的说法是，等一下。
Hang on.
等一下。
Or hang on a sec, which is hang on a second.
或者“hang on a sec”，也就是“hang on a second”。
All right.
好的。
That's all the words we have for today.
这就是我们今天要讲的所有内容。
Why don't we review our dialogue one last time?
我们最后再复习一遍对话好吗？
Ugh, this bathroom is a pig's die.
呃，这卫生间脏得像猪圈。
Helen, why do you keep flushing the toilet?
海伦，你为什么老冲马桶？
What's wrong?
怎么了？
I just can't stand it.
我就是受不了。
It's really gross in here.
这里太恶心了。
There's a stain on the toilet seat and the floor was wet and slippery, so I cleaned it.
马桶座上有污渍，地板又湿又滑，所以我清理了一下。
You did what?
你做了什么？
Helen, I know it's gross, but I've seen many public washrooms that are much worse.
海伦，我知道很恶心，但我见过比这糟糕得多的公共卫生间。
Why are you cleaning the countertop?
你为什么在擦台面？
Are you out of your mind?
你疯了吗？
I can't help myself.
我控制不住自己。
It's just so disgusting in here.
这里实在太恶心了。
Helen, this is not like your own bathroom.
海伦，这又不是你自己的卫生间。
Just leave it to the cleaners, OK?
留给清洁工处理吧，好吗？
Hang on.
等一下。
I'm just going to quickly wipe the sink and sweep the floor.
我很快擦一下水槽，再扫个地。
You're such a neat freak.
你真是个洁癖狂。
I'm out of here.
我走了。
All right, so talking about cleanliness and being neat, what type of person are you?
好的，说到清洁和整洁，你是什么类型的人？
Are you a neat freak?
你是洁癖狂吗？
Do you keep everything very clean and ordered?
你会把一切都保持得非常干净和有序吗？
I'm not a neat freak, but I'm also not a pig, not a slob.
我不是洁癖狂，但也不是猪，不是邋遢鬼。
I like things to be very organized.
我喜欢东西井井有条。
But I'm not really concerned about cleaning so much.
但我其实不太在意打扫。
I'm too lazy.
我太懒了。
So there's a difference for me.
所以对我来说有区别。
In my house, I know where everything is, but maybe there's clothes on the floor and there's
在我家，我知道每样东西在哪里，但可能地上有衣服，
books in the bathroom.
浴室里有书。
So I'm in the middle.
所以我处于中间状态。
What about you?
你呢？
Are you a neat freak?
你是洁癖狂吗？
No, I'm not really a neat freak per se, but I do like everything to be very clean, on
不，我严格来说不是洁癖狂，但我确实喜欢一切都很干净，
the other hand.
另一方面。
So I can't really stand it when things are...
所以我真的受不了东西...
If things are out of order a little bit, that's okay, but if things are dirty, that really
如果东西有点乱，那还行，但如果脏了，那真的
gets to me.
让我受不了。
But I'm not the type of person that has folders with all my bills in one folder or labels,
但我不是那种把所有账单都放在一个文件夹里或贴标签的人，
or even when I was in school, I didn't have my notebooks in order.
甚至上学时，我的笔记本也不是整整齐齐的。
Really?
真的吗？
So we're the opposite.
那我们正好相反。
Yeah, exactly.
是的，没错。
But I hate things that are dirty.
但我讨厌脏东西。
Interesting.
有意思。
Well, let us know, are you a neat freak?
好吧，告诉我们，你是洁癖狂吗？
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
我们的网站是EnglishPod.com。
You can talk about yourself all over that lesson comments area.
你可以在课程评论区域尽情谈论自己。
That's right.
没错。
And if you have any other suggestions or comments, we're always there as well.
如果你有其他建议或评论，我们也一直在那里。
And we'll see you guys next time.
我们下次再见。
Bye.
再见。
And thanks so much for watching.
非常感谢你们的观看。